Man has made his match... now it's his problem.
Blade Runner is a science fiction, drama,
thriller film directed by Ridley Scott.
In the smog-choked dystopian Los Angeles of 2019, blade runner Rick Deckard is called out of retirement to terminate a
quartet of replicants who have escaped to Earth seeking their creator for a way to extend their short life spans.
Deckard, played by Harrison Ford.
Batty, played by Rutger Hauer.
Rachael, played by Sean Young.
Gaff, played by Edward James Olmos.
Bryant, played by M. Emmet Walsh.
Pris, played by Daryl Hannah.
Blade Runner is a 1982 science fiction film directed by Ridley Scott
from a screenplay by Hampton Fancher and David Peoples.
Starring Harrison Ford, Rutger Hauer, Sean Young, and Edward
James Olmos, it is an adaptation of Philip K.
Dick's 1968 novel Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep?
The film is set in a dystopian future Los Angeles of 2019, in which synthetic humans known as
replicants are bio-engineered by the powerful Tyrell Corporation to work on space colonies.
When a fugitive group of advanced replicants led by Roy Batty (Hauer) escapes back to
Earth, former cop Rick Deckard (Ford) reluctantly agrees to hunt them down.
Blade Runner initially underperformed in North American theaters and polarized critics; some praised its
thematic complexity and visuals, while others critiqued its slow pacing and lack of action.
The film's soundtrack, composed by Vangelis, was nominated in 1982
for a BAFTA and a Golden Globe as best original score.
Blade Runner later became a cult film, and has since come to be
regarded as one of the greatest science fiction films.
Hailed for its production design depicting a high-tech but decaying future, the film is often regarded as
both a leading example of neo-noir cinema and a foundational work of the cyberpunk genre.
It has influenced many science fiction films, video
games, anime, and television series.
It also brought the work of Dick to Hollywood's attention and
led to several film adaptations of his works.
In 1993, it was selected for preservation in the National
Film Registry by the Library of Congress.
Seven different versions of Blade Runner exist as a result of
controversial changes requested by studio executives.
A director's cut was released in 1992 after a strong
response to test screenings of a workprint.
This, in conjunction with the film's popularity as a video rental,
made it one of the earliest films to be released on DVD.
In 2007, Warner Bros.
released The Final Cut, a 25th-anniversary digitally remastered version; this
is the only version over which Scott retained artistic control.
The film is the first of the franchise of the same name.
A sequel, titled Blade Runner 2049, was released in 2017 alongside a trilogy of short
films covering the thirty-year span between the two films' settings.
The anime series Blade Runner: Black Lotus was released in 2021.
The film explores themes of android, flying car, bounty
hunter, artificial intelligence (a.i.), genetics.
The tone is intense and dark and thought_provoking.